<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4001/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4001/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2021-04-23T08:33:21-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/feed.xml</id><title type="html">HyBlogLogy</title><subtitle>A blog about hydroclimatology, society, and tech.
</subtitle><author><name>Patrick Wurster</name><email>pmwurster@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Crop Condition Monitoring Using NASA’s SMAP Level-4 Carbon Product</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/blog/publications/2021-04-15-cropland-l4c/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crop Condition Monitoring Using NASA’s SMAP Level-4 Carbon Product" /><published>2021-04-15T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-04-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/blog/publications/cropland-l4c</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/blog/publications/2021-04-15-cropland-l4c/">&lt;p&gt;Above: Crop conditions represented by the SMAP Level-4 Carbon Product during mid-August in 2017. Red colors are indicating below normal conditions while blue colors indicate better than normal conditions. Notice the dark red area over the Northern Great Plains that coincided with a sever flash drought. Image by Patrick Wurster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A collaboration between the University of Montana’s Geosciences Department and the Numerical Terradynamic Simulation Group (NTSG) shows that the SMAP Level-4 Carbon Product, developed by NASA and the NTSG, provides valuable information on crop conditions over the course of the growing season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications&quot;&gt;Implications:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filling in knowledge gaps:&lt;/strong&gt; While the US provides a wealth of information on crop condition and more, many countries where agriculture is important do not have such resources. The L4C has the potential to fill this gap in countries where condition data is not available, which may work to improve global food security.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informing response:&lt;/strong&gt; The L4C can identify areas where crop production is more sensitive to climate anomalies and areas less effected, providing information to farmers and policy-makers about where to allocate valuable mitigation resources.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bridging different “ways of knowing”:&lt;/strong&gt; Farmers are experts in the cultivation of crops, and we integrate their knowledge into our scientific analysis. Integrating different “ways of knowing”, like farmer knowledge and science, is key to adapting to an uncertain future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;PROBLEM&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information on crop condition at high spatial and temporal scales over large regions or continents is important for understanding the impacts of climate anomalies on agriculture. The US Department of Agriculture (USDA) National Agricultural Statistics Service (NASS) does an excellent job of providing valuable crop data for the United States through their data portal &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickstats.nass.usda.gov/&quot;&gt;Quick Stats&lt;/a&gt;, including weekly crop condition reports. Crop conditions are assessed by farmers and other agricultural experts in terms of the field percent observed as “Excellent”, “Good”, “Fair”, “Poor”, or “Very Poor” which are provided to and reported by NASS. Detailed definitions of the crop condition categories are provided by NASS &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nass.usda.gov/Publications/National_Crop_Progress/terms_definitions.php#condition&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. However, there are two major limitations in using the crop condition reports for scientific analysis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The assessments are ordinal and subjective in nature (e.g., “Good” vs “Fair”), making quantitative analysis difficult.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The assessments are only available at the state-level, and not at county-level or finer spatial scales. The relatively rough spatial scale can be problematic in larger states with diverse climate conditions and farming practices. For example, crop conditions in Montana can vary widely between the wetter and cooler mountainous west where crops are primarily irrigated, and the dryer and warmer eastern praries where crops are primarily rain-fed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;SOLUTION&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first limitation was addressed by &lt;cite&gt;Begauria and Maneta, 2020&lt;/cite&gt;, who transformed the ordinal data into a continuous crop condition index (CCI) that isolated the effect of natural random variability (i.e., drought, disease, etc.). For example, the effect of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012%E2%80%9313_North_American_drought&quot;&gt;2012 drought&lt;/a&gt; can be observed in CCI values shown in Figure 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/Begauria2020_F3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Figure 1. Crop condition index (CCI) for corn in selected states over 2012. Portions of the US corn belt suffered a severe drought over the growing season, as indicated by negative (red) CCI values. Values around zero indicate the normal condition. Figure borrowed with permission from &lt;cite&gt;Begauria and Maneta (2020)&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8008865&quot;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Jones et al. (2017)&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt; developed the SMAP Level-4 Carbon Product (L4C), a satellite informed model that estimates carbon exchange components including gross primary production (GPP). The project was a collaboration between NASA and the NTSG. Gross primary production (GPP) is a good indicator of crop condition because it captures vegetation growth as the season progresses. The L4C was novel in that it incorporated soil moisture estimates provided by NASA’s Soil Moisture Active Passive satellite (SMAP). SMAP observes microwave radiation emitted by the Earth’s surface which is sensitive to soil moisture conditions in the top 5 cm of the soil. GPP is proportional to the available soil moisture, making soil moisture an important observation when estimating GPP. Continuous soil moisture observations provided by SMAP are very useful because in-situ observations are limited by sparse point measurements. The L4C also relies on available radiation, temperature, and vapor pressure deficit. The L4C provides daily estimates at up to a 1-km resolution for different biomes like forest, grassland, or crops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thought that anomalies in the accumulated GPP at different stages of the growing season would be a good indicator of crop condition. If so, then the L4C could provide a measure of crop condition over the growing season at a scale of around 1-km, or about 250 acres. This is much better than crop conditions at the state-level, or even county-level. Plus, the L4C data is available daily with global coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We compared anomalies in CCI to anomalies in the total GPP over croplands within each state for two broadleaf plant types (corn and soybeans) and two cereal plant types (barley and spring wheat) to see how well the L4C indicated crop conditions at the state-level. We found that the two were significantly correlated, particularly after around 6-8 weeks after planting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/Wurster2020b_F5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Figure 2. Correlations between the state-level CCI and total accumulated GPP anomaly aggregated within the corresponding state at key stages in growth development for (A) corn, (B) soybeans, (C) barley, and (D) spring wheat. Darker greens indicate better agreement and the black dots indicate a significant correlation. Borrowed with permission from &lt;cite&gt;Wurster et al. (2020) &lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The comparison between CCI and GPP anomalies showed that the L4C could provide information about crop condition at relatively high temporal scales (weekly), but the spatial scale remained relatively course (state-level). NASS also provides annual crop-yield data at the county-level, which provided the opportunity to compare the L4C to data and higher spatial resolutions, albeit at lower temporal resolution (annual as opposed to weekly). We compared weekly GPP anomalies provided by the L4C to annual crop yields at the county-level, and the results were similar to the comparison with CCI. Figure 3 shows the agreement between GPP anomalies and crop-yield anomalies at the county-level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/Wurster2020b_F3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Figure 3. Correlations between county-level yield anomalies and county-level GPP anomalies for (A) corn and (B) soybeans at key stages of the growing season. Greener colors indicate higher positive correlations, which tend to increase as the season progresses. Soybean yield anomalies tend to be more correlated with GPP anomalies than with corn. &lt;cite&gt;Wurster et al. (2020)&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;citations&quot;&gt;Citations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Begueria, S., and Maneta, M. M. (2020). Humans as sensors: qualitative crop condition
survey data reveals spatiotemporal production patterns and allows early yield predictions.
TBDProc. Natl. Acad. USA 117, 18317–18323. doi:10.1073/pnas.1917774117.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jones, L. A., Kimball, J. S., Reichle, R. H., Madani, N., Glassy, J., Ardizzone, J. V.,
et al. (2017). The SMAP level 4 carbon product for monitoring ecosystem land-
atmosphere CO2 exchange. IEEE Trans. Geosci. Rem. Sens. 55, 6517–6532.
doi:10.1109/TGRS.2017.2729343.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wurster, P., Maneta, M., Kimball, J.S., Endsley, K.A., Begueria, S. (2021). Monitoring crop status in the United States using the SMAP Level-4 Carbon Product. Front. Big Data 3:597720. doi:10.3389/fdata.2020.597720.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Patrick Wurster</name><email>pmwurster@gmail.com</email></author><category term="publications" /><summary type="html">Above: Crop conditions represented by the SMAP Level-4 Carbon Product during mid-August in 2017. Red colors are indicating below normal conditions while blue colors indicate better than normal conditions. Notice the dark red area over the Northern Great Plains that coincided with a sever flash drought. Image by Patrick Wurster.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/img/blog/GPP2017.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/img/blog/GPP2017.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>