<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2021-04-30T13:44:09-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">HyBlogLogy</title><subtitle>A blog about hydroclimatology, society, and tech.
</subtitle><author><name>Patrick Wurster</name><email>pmwurster@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Farmer Decision-making Mitigates the Impact of Drought on Crop Yield</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2021-04-20-crop-production-and-climate-anomalies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Farmer Decision-making Mitigates the Impact of Drought on Crop Yield" /><published>2021-04-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-04-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/crop-production-and-climate-anomalies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2021-04-20-crop-production-and-climate-anomalies/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many studies about the impacts of drought on agriculture focus on crop yield, or the crop produced per unit area. But this does not tell the entire story because farmers can offset crop yield losses during drought by increasing the planted area of a given crop at the beginning of the season, thus increasing the harvested area, thus increasing crop production (or total crop produced). Our research helped to fill in this gap by focusing on the impact of drought on crop production rather than crop yield. We also discuss how the affects of topography and irrigation might limit farmer decision-making in regards to crop production. Finally, we discuss that drought conditions are not the only factor that can impact crop production, and that the prices farmers receive for their produce is also plays a role in variability in crop production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We focused on the crop production of alfalfa, barley, and winter wheat grown in Montana, Idaho, Wyoming, North Dakota and South Dakota at the county scale to determine if farmers mitigate the impacts of drought on yields by increasing crop production. The study area is advantageous because of differences in climate and topography between the western and eastern parts of the region. The western part of the region is generally comprised of wetter, cooler mountainous terrain where crops are primarily irrigated. The east is generally dryer, warmer, and flatter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications&quot;&gt;Implications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informed decision making:&lt;/strong&gt; Farmers mitigate the impacts of drought on crop yield by adjusting the planted area of a given crop when low crop yields are expected.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Irrigation from mountain snowpack mutes the impact of drought:&lt;/strong&gt; Areas with irrigation infrastructure supplied by surrounding mountain snowpack provides a strong buffer against drought conditions. Farmers in the flatter Plains area do not enjoy this benefit because of lack of available mountain snowpack. Lack of irrigation limits decision making by farmers by limiting the available crops that can be grown during periods of drought.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Climate not the only factor:&lt;/strong&gt; Price is a more important consideration for some crops than others when farmers are making decisions. Prices impact crops for livestock feed less than crops for human consumption. For example, wheat production is more sensitive to prices than alfalfa. We posit that alfalfa is less tied to alfalfa prices because it is used for animal feed and so is more tied to animal prices and not crop prices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many studies have focused on the impacts of drought on crop yield, but we wondered if crop yields alone tells the whole story. Here, we make an important distinction: crop yields are defined as the production per unit area (e.g., bushels per acre, tonnes per hectare) and crop production is defined as the total weight or volume of food produced (e.g., bushels, tonnes). If we assume that, in most cases, farmers attempt to maximize crop yields given the climate condition, and so variability in crop yield is independent of farmer decision-making and is caused by climate anomalies. However, increasing the land that a farmer allocates to a given crop may compensate for losses in yield by increasing production. Or, a farmer may choose to grow a different crop altogether, perhaps a crop more resistant to drought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ask, can farmer-decisions regarding the amount of crop to produce mitigate the impacts of drought on crop yields?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-findings&quot;&gt;Our Findings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Droughts clearly have a negative impact on crop yield, which is defined as the mass or weight per unit area (e.g., bushels per acre). However, the impact of drought on crop production, defined as the total mass or weight of crop produced (e.g., bushels, tons) is less understood. Crop production is an important measure because it includes farmer decision-making, that is how much land to allocate to a given crop? For example, given the expectation of drought, a farmer could increase the cropping area to offset yield losses. The increase in cropping area might actually further decrease yield as cropping area is expanded into lower quality farming areas, yet production would increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We observed that crop production was more associated with droughts that persist over 7 to 9 months However, reductions in crop yield due to drought have been found to be more associated with droughts that persist for around 3 months (e.g., &lt;cite&gt;Zipper et al., (2016)&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Pena-Gallardo (2019)&lt;/cite&gt;). Therefore, crop yield responds more rapidly to drought than production, telling us that farmers are effectively mitigating the negative impacts of drought on crop yield through decisions-making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Farmers in the US generally purchase seed in the fall preceding the growing season, or months before the growing season begins. Assuming that farmers consider land allocation when making seed purchases, then farmers must have some expectation of crop yields months before the season begins, and they also must have some expectation of climate conditions for the following season when making their decisions about land allocation in the fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not the case in all areas of our study. Crop production experienced less reductions in response to drought in the western portion of the study area crops are primarily irrigated from available mountain snowpack. Production experienced greater declines in response to drought in the flatter areas where irrigation is limited by lack of mountain snowpack. This indicated to us that farmers in more mountainous areas have more flexibility in their decision-making than
farmers in rain-fed areas. This might help policy makers and farmers better understand where to direct limited resources during times of drought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, drought is not the only factor that farmers may consider when deciding about land allocation and crop production. Market conditions are also an important consideration. For example, a given crop might be expected to return higher yields during drought than an alternative crop, but the higher yielding crop may return a lower market value making the lower yielding crop more valuable. Therefore, the prices received by farmers for a given crop is an important consideration when determining the impact of drought on crop production.  We observed that prices were most important for wheat, followed by barley, and least for alfalfa. We posit that the importance of market-prices varied by crop for several different reasons. Alfalfa is a perennial crop produces for around 5-7 years, limiting the ability of farmers growing alfalfa to change to another crop. Second, alfalfa is used as animal feed, while wheat is primarily used for human consumption. Barley is used for both human and animal consumption. Crops used for animal feed are likely more tied to livestock prices than the sale price of alfalfa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;citations&quot;&gt;Citations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pena-Gallardo, Marina, Vicente-Serrano, S.M., Quiring, S., Svoboda, M., Hannaford, J.,
Tomas-Burguera, M., Martín-Hernández, N., Domínguez-Castro, F., El Kenawy, A.,
2018b. Response of crop yield to different time-scales of drought in the United States:
spatio-temporal patterns and climatic and environmental drivers. Agricultere and Forest Meteorololgy, 264, 40–55. Doi: 10.1016/j.agrformet.2018.09.019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wurster P., Maneta M., Beguerı́a S., Cobourn K., Maxwell B., Silverman N., Ewing S., Jensco K., Gardner P., Kimball J., Holden Z., Ji X., and Vicente-Serrano S. 2020. Characterizing the impact of climatic and price anomalies on agrosystems in the northwest United States. Agriculture and Forest Meteorology, 200. Doi: 10.1016/j.agrformet.2019.107778.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zipper, S.C., Qiu, J., Kucharik, C.J., 2016. Drought effects on US maize and soybean
production: spatiotemporal patterns and historical changes. Environmental Research Letters 11,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doi: 10.1088/1748-9326/11/9/094021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Patrick Wurster</name><email>pmwurster@gmail.com</email></author><category term="publications" /><summary type="html">Summary: Many studies about the impacts of drought on agriculture focus on crop yield, or the crop produced per unit area. But this does not tell the entire story because farmers can offset crop yield losses during drought by increasing the planted area of a given crop at the beginning of the season, thus increasing the harvested area, thus increasing crop production (or total crop produced). Our research helped to fill in this gap by focusing on the impact of drought on crop production rather than crop yield. We also discuss how the affects of topography and irrigation might limit farmer decision-making in regards to crop production. Finally, we discuss that drought conditions are not the only factor that can impact crop production, and that the prices farmers receive for their produce is also plays a role in variability in crop production.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/img/blog/irrigation.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/img/blog/irrigation.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Crop Condition Monitoring Using NASA’s SMAP Level-4 Carbon Product</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2021-04-15-cropland-l4c/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crop Condition Monitoring Using NASA’s SMAP Level-4 Carbon Product" /><published>2021-04-15T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-04-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/cropland-l4c</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/publications/2021-04-15-cropland-l4c/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A collaboration between my research group and the Numerical Terradynamic Simulation Group (NTSG) shows that the SMAP Level-4 Carbon Product, developed by NASA and the NTSG, provides valuable information on crop conditions at higher spatial and temporal resolution than what is currently available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications&quot;&gt;Implications:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filling in knowledge gaps:&lt;/strong&gt; Weekly crop condition reports available in the US are only available for individual states and is not available at the county-level. The course spatial scale may not fully capture crop conditions, particularly in larger states where crop conditions vary from place to place. Our research shows the L4C can provide information about crop condition at finer spatial scales than what is currently available. Additionally, Many countries across the world where agriculture is important do not have comprehensive data on crop condition. The L4C has the potential to fill this gap which can improve global food security.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bridging different “ways of knowing”:&lt;/strong&gt; Farmers are experts in the cultivation of crops, and we integrate their knowledge into our scientific analysis. Integrating different “ways of knowing” like farmer knowledge and western science, is key to adapting to an uncertain future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;PROBLEM&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information on crop condition at high spatial and temporal scales over large regions or continents is important for understanding the impacts of climate anomalies on agriculture. The US Department of Agriculture (USDA) National Agricultural Statistics Service (NASS) does an excellent job of providing valuable information on crop condition for the United States through their data portal &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickstats.nass.usda.gov/&quot;&gt;Quick Stats&lt;/a&gt;. Crop conditions are assessed by farmers and other agricultural experts in terms of the field percent observed as “Excellent”, “Good”, “Fair”, “Poor”, or “Very Poor” which are provided to and reported by NASS. Detailed definitions of the crop condition categories are provided by NASS &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nass.usda.gov/Publications/National_Crop_Progress/terms_definitions.php#condition&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. However, there are two major limitations in using the crop condition reports for scientific analysis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The assessments are ordinal and subjective in nature (e.g., “Good” vs “Fair”), making quantitative analysis difficult.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The assessments are only available at the state-level, and not at county-level or finer spatial scales. The relatively rough spatial scale can be problematic in larger states with diverse climate conditions and farming practices. For example, crop conditions in Montana can vary widely between the wetter and cooler mountainous west where crops are primarily irrigated, and the dryer and warmer eastern praries where crops are primarily rain-fed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;SOLUTION&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first limitation was addressed by &lt;cite&gt;Begauria and Maneta, 2020&lt;/cite&gt;, who transformed the ordinal data into a continuous crop condition index (CCI) that isolated the effect of natural random variability (i.e., drought, disease, etc.). For example, the effect of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012%E2%80%9313_North_American_drought&quot;&gt;2012 drought&lt;/a&gt; can be observed in CCI values shown in Figure 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/Begauria2020_F3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Figure 1. Crop condition index (CCI) for corn in selected states over 2012. Portions of the US corn belt suffered a severe drought over the growing season, as indicated by negative (red) CCI values. Values around zero indicate the normal condition. Figure borrowed with permission from &lt;cite&gt;Begauria and Maneta (2020)&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8008865&quot;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Jones et al. (2017)&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt; developed the SMAP Level-4 Carbon Product (L4C), a satellite informed model that estimates carbon exchange components including gross primary production (GPP). The project was a collaboration between NASA and the NTSG. Gross primary production (GPP) is a good indicator of crop condition because it captures vegetation growth as the season progresses. The L4C was novel in that it incorporated soil moisture estimates provided by NASA’s Soil Moisture Active Passive satellite (SMAP). SMAP observes microwave radiation emitted by the Earth’s surface which is sensitive to soil moisture conditions in the top 5 cm of the soil. GPP is proportional to the available soil moisture, making soil moisture an important observation when estimating GPP. Continuous soil moisture observations provided by SMAP are very useful because in-situ observations are limited by sparse point measurements. The L4C also relies on available radiation, temperature, and vapor pressure deficit. The L4C provides daily estimates at up to a 1-km resolution for different biomes like forest, grassland, or crops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thought that anomalies in the accumulated GPP at different stages of the growing season would be a good indicator of crop condition. If so, then the L4C could provide a measure of crop condition over the growing season at a scale of around 1-km, or about 250 acres. This is much better than crop conditions at the state-level, or even county-level. Plus, the L4C data is available daily with global coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We compared anomalies in CCI to anomalies in the total GPP over croplands within each state for two broadleaf plant types (corn and soybeans) and two cereal plant types (barley and spring wheat) to see how well the L4C indicated crop conditions at the state-level. We found that the two were significantly correlated, particularly after around 6-8 weeks after planting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/Wurster2020b_F5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Figure 2. Correlations between the state-level CCI and total accumulated GPP anomaly aggregated within the corresponding state at key stages in growth development for (A) corn, (B) soybeans, (C) barley, and (D) spring wheat. Darker greens indicate better agreement and the black dots indicate a significant correlation. Borrowed with permission from &lt;cite&gt;Wurster et al. (2020) &lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The comparison between CCI and GPP anomalies showed that the L4C could provide information about crop condition at relatively high temporal scales (weekly), but the spatial scale remained relatively course (state-level). So, we also used annual crop-yield data provided by NASS at the county-level, which provided the opportunity to compare the L4C to data and higher spatial resolutions, albeit at lower temporal resolution (annual as opposed to weekly). The results from the yeild analysis were similar to the comparison with CCI. Figure 3 shows the agreement between GPP anomalies and crop-yield anomalies at the county-level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/Wurster2020b_F3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Figure 3. Correlations between county-level yield anomalies and county-level GPP anomalies for (A) corn and (B) soybeans at key stages of the growing season. Greener colors indicate higher positive correlations, which tend to increase as the season progresses. Soybean yield anomalies tend to be more correlated with GPP anomalies than with corn. &lt;cite&gt;Wurster et al. (2020)&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our comparison between GPP anomalies estimated by the L4C and both weekly crop condition anomalies at the state-level and annual yield anomalies at the county-level showed that the SMAP L4C can provide valuable information on crop condition at higher temporal and spatial resolution that what is currently available at the time of this writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;citations&quot;&gt;Citations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Begueria, S., and Maneta, M. M. (2020). Humans as sensors: qualitative crop condition
survey data reveals spatiotemporal production patterns and allows early yield predictions.
TBDProc. Natl. Acad. USA 117, 18317–18323. doi:10.1073/pnas.1917774117.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jones, L. A., Kimball, J. S., Reichle, R. H., Madani, N., Glassy, J., Ardizzone, J. V.,
et al. (2017). The SMAP level 4 carbon product for monitoring ecosystem land-
atmosphere CO2 exchange. IEEE Trans. Geosci. Rem. Sens. 55, 6517–6532.
doi:10.1109/TGRS.2017.2729343.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wurster, P., Maneta, M., Kimball, J.S., Endsley, K.A., Begueria, S. (2021). Monitoring crop status in the United States using the SMAP Level-4 Carbon Product. Front. Big Data 3:597720. doi:10.3389/fdata.2020.597720.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Patrick Wurster</name><email>pmwurster@gmail.com</email></author><category term="publications" /><summary type="html">Summary: A collaboration between my research group and the Numerical Terradynamic Simulation Group (NTSG) shows that the SMAP Level-4 Carbon Product, developed by NASA and the NTSG, provides valuable information on crop conditions at higher spatial and temporal resolution than what is currently available.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/img/blog/smap_jpl.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/img/blog/smap_jpl.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>